Edmund! Get away from there!
爱德蒙！快过来！
Peter! What do you think you're doing?
彼得！你怎么这么不懂事？
Peter, quickly, the shelter. Now!
彼得，快！ 带你弟弟躲到安全的地方去！
- Come on! - Wait...
- 快！ - 等下...
Come on, leave it!
快，离开这里！
Mommy!
妈咪！
Lucy, come on!
露西，快跟我来！
- Come on, quickly! - Run!
- 快，快点儿！ - 快跑！
- Hurry! - Mum!
- 快啊！ - 妈妈！
- Wait! Dad! - Ed!
- 等等，爹地... - 爱德蒙！
- Edmund, no! - I'll get him!
- 爱德蒙，别回去！ - 我去拉他回来！
- Peter, come back! - Ed! Come here!
- 彼得，回来！ - 爱德蒙！过来！
Edmund! Get down!
爱德蒙！快趴下！
Come on, you idiot, run!
跟我走， 你这傻瓜，快！
Get out!
快跑！
Come on!
快过来！
Hurry!
赶紧！
Why can't you think of anyone but yourself? You're so selfish!
你就不能为别人考虑考虑吗？ 真是个自私鬼！
- You could've got us killed! - Stop it!
- 就因为你，大家都会有生命危险！ - 别说了
It's OK.
没关系的，嘘...
Why can't you just do as you're told?
你就不能乖乖听话吗？
Alms for the poor. Alms for the poor.
可怜可怜穷苦人吧...
God bless you, sir.
上帝保佑您，先生...
Children and evacuation staff...
儿童以及撤离人员家属...
You need to keep this on, darling. All right?
亲爱的，别脱衣服，好吗？ 会着凉的...
You warm enough? Good girl.
够暖和么？乖孩子...
Say hello to Auntie Laura. Goodbye, darling, we love you.
和劳拉姑姑问好， 再见，亲爱的，我们爱你...
- Dad wouldn't make us go. - If Dad were here,
爹地在的话， 是不会让我们走的
You will listen to your brother, won't you, Edmund?
乖乖听哥哥的话， 好吗，爱德蒙？
Promise me you'll look after the others.
答应我，一定照顾好他们...
I will, Mum.
我会的，妈妈...
- Good man. - All aboard! All aboard!
- 好孩子 - 请大家排队上车！...
- Bye, darling! - Bye!
- 再见，亲爱的！ - 拜拜！
Susan.
苏珊
Be a big girl.
坚强些，懂事点儿...
Hold on to your brother's hand. Don't let it go.
抓紧哥哥的手...
All right. Off you go.
好啦，你们去吧
- All aboard! - Bye-bye. Love you.
- 请大家上车... - 拜拜，我们爱你...
Hey, get off. I know how to get on a train by myself.
嘿，别扯我啊， 我知道怎么上火车！
Get off me!
别拉着我！
May I have your tickets, please? Tickets, please.
我能看看您的车票吗？ 请出示车票...
Peter.
彼得
- That's right. On you go. - Yes. Thank you.
- 可以了，你们可以上车了... - 好的，谢谢
Come on, Lucy. We have to stick together now.
好啦，露西...离开了妈妈， 什么事儿都得靠我们自己了
Everything's gonna be all right. It's gonna be fine.
没事的，不用怕
Bye, Mommy! I love you!
拜拜，妈咪！我爱您！
- Bye-bye, dear. - Bye! We'll miss you! See you soon.
- 再见，亲爱的... - 我们会想您的！再见！
- I love you, Mum! Bye! - See you soon!
- 我爱您，妈妈！再见！ - 再见...
- Write to us, Mum! - Love you!
- 要给我们写信啊，妈妈！ - 我爱你们！...
Goosey Station. Goosey Station.
Goosey站，Goosey站...
Give me your hand. Let's get going.
拉上我的手... 我们走吧！
The professor knew we were coming.
教授知道我们会来吧...
Perhaps we've been incorrectly labeled.
会不会是标签上地点写错了...？
And whoa. Whoa.
喔...
- Mrs. Macready? - I'm afraid so.
- 麦克里迪女士？ - 没错儿
Is this it, then? Haven't you brought anything else?
就这样？ 没其他东西了？
No, ma'am.
没...
It's just us.
就我们四个...
Small favors.
那就好
Come on. Good girl. Come on. Come on.
驾，乖孩子... 驾，驾...
Professor Kirke is not accustomed to havin' children in this house.
科克教授这里不常有孩子光临...
And, as such, there are a few rules we need to follow.
尽管如此... 你们还是得乖乖的守些规矩
There will no shoutin'.
屋子里禁止高声喧哗...
Or runnin'. No improper use of the dumbwaiter.
...也不准到处乱跑...除非进餐时间， 平时不可以随便摆弄小升降梯（送饭菜用）
No touchin' of the historical artifacts!
不准...碰古工艺品！
And above all,
总之，一句话...
there shall be no disturbin' of the professor.
...你们不可以打扰到教授的工作
German aircraft carried out a number of attacks on Great Britain last night.
“昨夜，德国轰炸机...
The raids, which lasted for several hours...
轰炸持续了数小时之久...”
The sheets feel scratchy.
睡这被子，我觉得痒痒的...
Wars don't last forever, Lucy. We'll be home soon.
战争不会持续多久的，露西 我们很快就可以回家了...
- Yeah, if home's still there. - Isn't it time you were in bed?
- 是啊，如果家还在的话... - 这时候你是不是该上床睡觉了？！
- Yes, Mum. - Ed!
- 遵命，“妈妈”！ - 爱德蒙！
You saw outside. This place is huge.
你该去四处瞧瞧 这地方可宽敞了！
We can do whatever we want here.
我们爱怎么折腾就怎么折腾！
Tomorrow's going to be great.
明天我们会玩得很开心的！
Really.
相信我
"Gastrovascular."
“（器官）消化及循环双重职能的”...
Come on, Peter. Gastrovascular.
认识么，彼得，
- Is it Latin? - Yes.
- 是拉丁文吗？ - 没错儿
Is it Latin for "worst game ever invented"?
在拉丁文中，是不是 “有史以来发明的最无聊游戏”的意思？
We could play hide and seek.
我们玩捉迷藏好了～
But we're already having so much fun.
这个游戏我们不是玩得挺开心吗？
Come on, Peter, please.
来玩吧，彼得，求你了
Pretty please?
我真的很想玩儿...
- One, two, three, four, - What?
- 1，2，3，4... - 什么？...
nine, ten, 11...
9，10，11...
...24, 25, 26...
...24，25，26...
I was here first!
我先找到这里的！
...75, 76, 77, 78, 79, 80,
...75，76，77，78，79，80...
81, 82, 83, 84,
81，82，83，84...
85, 86, 85, 86, 87, 88,
85，86，85，86，87，88...
89, 90, 91, 92,
...89，90，91，92...
93, 94, 95...
93，94，95...
Were you hiding from me?
你是在躲着我么？
No.
哪里...
Well...
呃，喔...
I just... I...
我只是...我...
No. No. I just...
不...我...只是...
I was just... I didn't want to scare you.
我只是，呃... 不想吓着你...
If you don't mind my asking... what are you?
不介意我问问...你是谁吧？
Well, I'm a... Well, I'm a faun.
喔，我是...我是只半人羊... （古罗马神话中半人半羊状的农牧神）
And what about you?
...你呢？
You must be some kind of beardless dwarf?
你是个...年幼的小矮人？
I'm not a dwarf! I'm a girl!
我才不是小矮人呢！ 我是个小女孩！
And, actually, I'm tallest in my class.
而且，我还是班上最高的呢！
You mean to say that you're a Daughter of Eve?
你是说... 你是“夏娃之女”？
Well, my mum's name is Helen.
喔，我妈妈的名字是海伦
Yes, but you are in fact human.
对， 可...你是...人类？
Yes, of course.
是啊，当然...
What are you doing here?
你来这里做什么？
Well, I was hiding in the wardrobe in the spare room, and...
喔，我在玩捉迷藏的时候， 躲进了一间空屋的衣橱里...
Spare Oom? Is that in Narnia?
“Spare Oom”？（他将Room听成Oom） 这也是纳尼亚的某个地方吗？
Narnia? What's that?
纳尼亚？那是什么地方？
Well, dear girl, you're in it.
喔，亲爱的，你正身处其中呢！
Everything from the lamppost
从这根路灯柱到...
all the way to Castle Cair Paravel on the Eastern Ocean,
位于东海岸的卡尔城堡...
every stick and stone you see,
你所能瞧见的每一棵树木， 每一块石头...
every icicle is Narnia.
每一缕冰柱... 都是纳尼亚的一部分！
This is an awfully big wardrobe.
这衣橱可真大啊...
War Drobe? I'm sorry.
衣橱？差点儿忘了...
Please allow me to introduce myself. My name is Tumnus.
请允许我介绍一下自己， 我的名字是汤姆那斯
Pleased to meet you, Mr. Tumnus. I'm Lucy Pevensie.
很高兴认识你，汤姆那斯先生， 我是露西 佩文西
- Oh, you shake it. - Why?
- 噢，你得握着我的手，还要摇一摇 - 呃...为什么？
I... I don't know.
我...我也不知道
People do it when they meet each other.
反正大家见面时都这样做
Well, then, Lucy Pevensie from the shining city of War Drobe
喔，那么...来自“Spare Oom”大陆...
in the wondrous land of Spare Oom,
...奇妙“衣橱城”的露西 佩文西小姐...
how would it be if you came and had tea with me?
你是否愿意和我一起喝杯茶呢？
Well, thank you very much, but I...
喔，谢谢你的好意， 不过...
I probably should be getting back.
...我可能得回去了..
It's only just around the corner. And there'll be a glorious fire
我家很近，就在拐角那儿
with toast and tea and cakes.
你可以在温暖的篝火旁一边品味清香的茶 一边品尝美味的蛋糕和土司
And, perhaps, we'll even break into the sardines.
还有，或许... 我们还能吃上点儿沙丁鱼...
- I don't know. - Come on.
- 我不知道... - 来吧
It's not every day that I get to make a new friend.
我可是很少有机会 能认识新朋友的喔
Well, I suppose I could come for a little while.
喔，或许，去你那儿呆上一会儿 也没什么大不了的...
If you have sardines.
...只要...你有沙丁鱼！
By the bucketload.
有好几桶呢～
You all right?
- 不累吧？ - 嗯...
Well, here we are.
喔，我们到了
- After you. - May I help you with that?
- 你先进去 - 我来帮你拿吧
Thank you very much.
- 谢谢了 - 噢
Now, that... that is my father.
那...那是我父亲
He has a nice face.
他可真慈祥
He looks a lot like you.
看起来和你很像呢
No.
不...
No, I'm not very much like him at all, really.
不，事实上我和他并不十分相像...
My father's fighting in the war.
我爸爸还在打仗上呢...
My father went away to war too.
我爸爸也打过仗！
But that was a long, long time ago.
可那是很久很久以前的事儿了...
- Before this dreadful winter. - Winter's not all bad.
- 在这个该死的寒冬之前... - 冬天也不是那么令人讨厌
There's ice skating and snowball fights.
大家可以滑冰，打雪仗什么的...
No. No, we haven't had a Christmas in a hundred years.
不，实际上，我们这儿 已经有一百年没过圣诞了...
What? No presents for a hundred years?
什么？已经有一百年 没收到过圣诞礼物了？
Always winter, never Christmas.
冬季的绵延， 淡化了人们心中圣诞的概念
It's been a long winter.
真是个漫长的冬季啊...
But you would have loved Narnia in summer.
不过，相信你会喜欢夏季的纳尼亚
We fauns danced with the dryads all night,
我们常与森林女神联欢...
and, you know, we never got tired.
不知疲倦地彻夜共舞...
And music. Oh, such music!
还有音乐！噢，那么动听的音乐！
Would... would you like to hear some now?
你...现在想听听吗？
Now, are you familiar
你听说过...
- with any Narnian lullabies? - Sorry, no.
- ...纳尼亚摇篮曲吗？ - 抱歉，不大熟悉...
Well, that's good.
喔，没关系
Because this... probably won't sound anything like one.
因为...我将为你演奏的旋律， 定会令你有耳目一新的感觉
- Oh, I should go. - It's too late for that now.
- 噢，我该走了 - 可现在已经很迟了
I'm such a terrible faun.
我真是个坏蛋
Oh, no.
噢，不
You're the nicest faun I've ever met.
你是我见过最友好的半人羊了！
Then I'm afraid you've had a very poor sampling.
或许你先前遇到的 比起我来更不如
No. You can't have done anything that bad.
不，你没做什么坏事儿啊！
It's not something I have done, Lucy Pevensie.
那不是我做过的事，露西 佩文西
It's something I am doing.
我正在做的事， 才让我自己觉得羞愧
What are you doing?
什么是“你正在做的事”？
I'm kidnapping you.
我在试图诱骗你...
It was the White Witch.
这是白巫婆的指令...
She's the one who makes it always winter, always cold. She gave orders.
就是她 让这里变成死寂而苍茫的严冬
If any of us ever find a human wandering in the woods,
如果我们谁在林子里遇见了迷路的人类
we're supposed to turn it over to her.
就得捉住他们，送去给她处置
But, Mr. Tumnus, you wouldn't.
可是，汤姆那斯先生 你才不会这样做呢！
I thought you were my friend.
你不是我的朋友吗
Now. She may already know you're here.
现在，她或许已经知道你在这儿了
The woods are full of her spies.
森林里布满了她的眼线
Even some of the trees are on her side.
甚至有些树木都在帮她秘密监视着
Can you find your way back from here?
你能自个儿找到回去的路吗？
- I think so. - All right.
- 我想可以 - 那好
Will you be all right?
你不会有事吧？
Hey, hey, hey.
嘿，嘿...
I'm sorry. I'm so sorry.
对不起，我很抱歉...
Here.
给你
Keep it. You need it more than I do.
留着吧， 你比我更需要它
No matter what happens, Lucy Pevensie, I am glad to have met you.
无论发生什么，露西・佩文西
You've made me feel warmer than I've felt in a hundred years.
与你相处的短暂时光中我体会到的温暖 甚至让我忘记了在这百年寒冬中的煎熬...
Now go.
回去吧
Go!
快！
Ready or not, here I come!
准备好了？我来了喔！
It's all right! I'm back! I'm all right!
我没事儿！我回来了！我很好！
Shut up! He's coming!
闭嘴！他就要来了！
You know, I'm not sure you two have quite got the idea of this game.
你们俩...知道捉迷藏该怎么玩儿吧？
Weren't you wondering where I was?
到处都找不到我 你难道不觉得奇怪吗？
That's the point. That was why he was seeking you.
本来就该这样啊！你躲得越隐秘 他就越找不到你，这样才有趣嘛
Does this mean I win?
那算我赢了吧？
I don't think Lucy wants to play anymore.
看来露西不想玩儿了
I've been gone for hours.
我都离开好几个小时了！
Lucy, the only wood in here is the back of the wardrobe.
露西，这里唯一的“树木” 就是衣橱的背面....
One game at a time, Lu. We don't all have your imagination.
是你说要玩捉迷藏的，怎么又搞出这么多花样 我们可没你那么丰富的想象力
But I wasn't imagining!
可那不是我的幻想！
That's enough, Lucy.
露西，够了
I wouldn't lie about this!
我何必要撒谎呢？！
Well, I believe you.
喔，我相信你
- You do? - Yeah, of course.
- 你相信我？ - 当然
Didn't I tell you about the field in the cupboards?
记得我和你提到过的那个 碗橱里的广场吗？
Will you just stop?
你闹够了没有？
You just have to make everything worse, don't you?
还嫌不够乱吗？
- It was just a joke! - When are you gonna learn to grow up?
- 我只不过开个玩笑！ - 你什么时候才能学着懂事点儿呢？
Shut up! You think you're Dad, but you're not!
闭嘴！你以为你是爹地 可你不是！
Well, that was nicely handled.
喔，这下可好
But... it really was there.
可是...那儿真的有个新世界呢！
Susan's right, Lucy.
苏珊说得没错，露西...
That's enough.
到此为止吧
Lucy.
露西
Where are you?
你在哪儿？
Hope you're not afraid of the dark.
希望你不会怕黑喔
Lucy!
露西！
Lucy.
露西
Where are you?
你在哪儿？
I think I believe you now.
现在我相信你了，出来吧！
Lucy.
露西
Lucy?
露西？
- Leave me alone! - What is it now, Ginarrbrik?
- 放开我！ - 怎么了，Ginarrbrik？
Make him let me go! I didn't do anything wrong!
让他放我走吧！ 我没做什么错事！
How dare you address the Queen of Narnia?
你竟敢支使纳尼亚女王？
I didn't know!
我又不知道！
- You will know her better hereafter! - Wait!
- 那就乖乖记牢，如果你还有下次机会的话！ - 等等！
What is your name, Son of Adam?
你叫什么名字，“亚当之子”？
And how, Edmund, did you come to enter my dominion?
那么，爱德蒙 你是怎么踏入我的国土的？
I'm not sure. I was just following my sister.
我也不知道... 我就是跟着我的妹妹
- Your sister? How many are you? - Four.
- 你的妹妹？你们有几个人？ - 4个
Lucy's the only one that's been here before.
露西是唯一曾到过这儿的
She said she met some faun called Tumnus.
她还说认识了一个叫汤姆那斯的 半人羊朋友
Peter and Susan didn't believe her. I didn't either.
彼得和苏珊不相信她 我也是...
Edmund, you look so cold. Will you come and sit with me?
爱德蒙，你觉得冷吧 愿意过来和我坐一块儿吗？
Now, how about something hot to drink?
想喝点儿热饮暖暖吗？
Yes, please, Your Majesty.
好的... 谢谢，尊敬的陛下
Your drink, sire.
你的饮料，阁下
How did you do that?
您是怎么做到的？
I can make anything you like.
我可以变出任何你喜欢的东西
Can you make me taller?
能让我长高些吗？
Anything you'd like to eat.
...任何你想吃的
Turkish delight?
土耳其软糖，可以吗？
Edmund?
爱德蒙？
I would very much like to meet the rest of your family.
我很想见见你的兄弟姐妹
Why?
为什么？
They're nothing special.
他们也没啥特别的
Oh, I'm sure they're not nearly as delightful as you are.
噢，我也觉得他们 不会比你更讨人喜欢
But you see, Edmund, I have no children of my own.
可是...爱德蒙 要知道我没有自己的孩子...
And you are exactly the sort of boy
而你正是我一直在寻找的男孩...
who I could see, one day, becoming Prince of Narnia.
我希望你有一天能登上 纳尼亚的王位...
Maybe even King.
甚至成为这里的最高统治者
Really?
真的吗？
Of course, you'd have to bring your family.
当然，所以你得把 你的家人一起带来
Do you mean, Peter would be king too?
你是说，彼得也会成为国王？
No! No, no.
不！不，不...
But a king needs servants.
国王不是需要仆人的吗
I guess I could bring 'em.
我想我会把他们带来的
Beyond these woods, you see those two hills?
你能透过树林，瞧见那两座小山吗？
My house is right between them.
我的宫殿就坐落其中
You'd love it there, Edmund.
你会喜欢那儿的，爱德蒙
It has whole rooms simply stuffed with Turkish delight.
在我那儿 有整间整间的土耳其软糖
- Couldn't I have some more now? - No!
- 现在不能再给我变出点儿吗？ - 不！
Don't want to ruin your appetite.
现在吃太多，到时就没胃口了不是？
Besides, you and I are going to be seeing each other again very soon.
何况我们应该很快又能见面了
I hope so, Your Majesty.
希望如此 尊敬的陛下
Until then, dear one. I'm gonna miss you.
再见，亲爱的 嗯...我会想你的
Edmund?
爱德蒙？
Oh, Edmund! You got in too!
噢，爱德蒙！你也进来了！
Isn't it wonderful?
这地方很棒吧！
- Where have you been? - With Mr. Tumnus. He's fine.
- 你上哪儿去了？ - 去汤姆那斯先生那儿了，他人很好！
The White Witch hasn't found out anything about him meeting me.
白巫婆还不知道他和我见面的事儿呢
The White Witch?
白巫婆？
She calls herself the Queen of Narnia, but she really isn't.
她称自己为纳尼亚女王， 可实际上并不是！
Are you all right? You look awful.
没事吧？看起来你脸色很不好
Well, what'd you expect? I mean, it's freezing.
喔，你说呢？ 这儿这么冷....
- How do we get out of here? - Come on.
- 我们怎么回去？ - 跟我来
This way.
这边走
Peter, Peter, wake up! Peter, wake up!
彼得，彼得，快醒醒！ 彼得，快醒醒！
It's there! It's really there!
- 它存在！它确实存在！ - 嘘...
- Lucy, what are you talking about? - Narnia!
- 露西，你在说什么呢？ - 纳尼亚！
It's all in the wardrobe like I told you!
在衣橱里，真的存在我告诉过你的 那另外一个世界！
- You've just been dreaming, Lucy. - But I haven't!
- 你是不是又做梦了，露西 - 那不是梦！
I saw Mr. Tumnus again! And this time Edmund went too.
我又见到汤姆那斯先生了！ 还有，这次爱德蒙也到了那里
You... You saw the faun?
你...也见到那只半人羊了？
Well, he didn't actually go there with me.
喔，事实上， 他并不是和我一起去的
He...
他...
What were you doing, Edmund?
你那时在做什么，爱德蒙？
I was just playing along.
就自己一个人玩儿啊
I'm sorry, Peter.
对不起，彼得
I shouldn't have encouraged her,
我真不该和她一起胡闹
but you know what little children are like these days.
可是要知道， 现在的孩子们都这么调皮...
They just don't know when to stop pretending.
总是不知道何时该适可而止
You children are one shenanigan shy of sleepin' in the stable!
你们这些不听话的孩子 是不是非要让我把你们赶到马厩里才能安静些！
Professor. I'm sorry. I told them you were not to be disturbed.
教授...对不起 我告诉过他们不要打扰您的
It's all right, Mrs. Macready. I'm sure there's an explanation.
没关系，麦克里迪女士 我相信他们也不是有意的
But first of all, I think this one is in need of a little hot chocolate.
你先帮我给这位小女士 泡杯热巧克力吧
Come along, dear.
过来，亲爱的...
You seem to have upset the delicate internal balance of my housekeeper.
我的管家似乎被你们烦得够呛 变得有些歇斯底里了...
We're very sorry, sir. It won't happen again.
很抱歉，先生 我们保证，以后不会这样了
It's our sister, sir. Lucy.
那都是因为我们的小妹妹露西，先生
- The weeping girl. - Yes, sir.
- 那个哭鼻子的小女孩？ - 是的，先生
- She's upset. - Hence the weeping.
- 她很难过... - 所以就哭鼻子了
It's nothing.
没什么大不了的
- We can handle it. - Oh, I can see that.
- 我们自己能解决 - 噢，是吗...
She thinks she's found a magical land.
她说她发现了一片魔幻大陆...
In the upstairs wardrobe.
就在楼上的衣橱中！
What did you say?
什么？
Lucy thinks she's found a forest inside.
露西说她在其中发现了一片森林！
She won't stop going on about it.
还固执地要我们相信她
- What was it like? - Like talking to a lunatic.
- 什么样的？ - 我们就像在和一个疯子交谈...
No, no, no, not her. The forest.
不，不，不，不是问她的情况， 我想听听她描述的森林是什么样的？
- You're not saying you believe her? - You don't?
- 您相信她说的是真的？ - 你们不相信她吗？
But of course not.
当然不
I mean, logically, it's impossible.
至少，从理论上说... （衣橱中的新世界）这不可能
What do they teach in schools these days?
现在的老师都是怎么教育孩子的啊...
Edmund said they were only pretending.
爱德蒙说 她只是在和我们耍调皮
He's usually the more truthful one, is he?
通常你们更信任他么？
No. This would be the first time.
不，这是头一回...
Well, if she's not mad and she's not lying,
喔，要是她没有什么不正常的话 我相信她并没有说谎...
then logically we must assume she's telling the truth.
而且，理论上 我们也最好接受她的说法
You're saying that we should just believe her?
您是说，我们该相信她？
She's your sister, isn't she? You're her family.
她是你们的妹妹 你们的亲人
You might just try acting like one.
至少你们该装作相信她...
Peter winds up, poised to take yet another wicket!
彼得奋力一掷， 成功淘汰又一个击球者！
Why can't we play hide and seek again?
为什么不玩捉迷藏了？
I thought you said it was a kid's game.
你不是说玩那游戏太幼稚了么？
Besides, we could all use the fresh air.
何况，到户外来呼吸点儿新鲜空气 也未尝不是件好事儿！
It's not like there isn't air inside.
屋子里又不是呼吸不到新鲜空气...
- Are you ready? - Are you?
- 准备好了？ - 扔吧
- Well done, Ed. - You bowled it!
- 干的漂亮，爱德蒙 - 球你扔的啊！
- What on earth is goin' on? - The Macready!
- 又怎么了？！ - 是麦克里迪女士！
Come on!
快跑！
No, no, back, back, back!
不，不行，往回，回去...！
- Come on! - You've got to be joking.
- 快过来啊！ - 呃，你不是开玩笑吧？！
Get back!
往里面点儿！
- My toe! - I'm not on your toe!
- 我的脚丫！ - 我没踩到你呢！
- Move back. - Will you stop shoving?
- 往里面点儿 - 别推啊！
Don't worry.
别想太多了
I'm sure it's just your imagination.
这不过是你们的臆想罢了
I don't suppose saying we're sorry
我很想为我们的自以为是 对你造成的伤害说抱歉
- would quite cover it. - No. It wouldn't.
- 尽管这确实难以原谅... - 是啊，确实难以原谅...
But that might!
- 不过...这样就没事儿了！ - 噢！
Stop it!
别闹了！
You little liar.
你这小骗子
- You didn't believe her, either. - Apologize to Lucy.
- 你们还不也不相信她 - 快向露西道歉
- Say you're sorry. - All right! I'm sorry.
- 快说对不起！ - 好啦！我很抱歉！
That's all right.
没关系
Some children just don't know when to stop pretending.
有些孩子就是不知道何时该适可而止
Oh, very funny.
噢，很有趣
Maybe we should go back.
或许我们该回去了
But shouldn't we at least take a look around?
不四处看看吗？
I think Lucy should decide.
我觉得，这该由露西决定
I'd like you all to meet Mr. Tumnus!
我带你们去见汤姆那斯先生吧！
Well, then Mr. Tumnus it is.
喔，那么... 汤姆那斯先生，有客人光临啦！
But we can't go hiking in the snow dressed like this.
难道我们得就穿得这么单薄 在雪地里走吗？
No.
当然不
But I'm sure the professor wouldn't mind us using these.
而且，我想，教授是不会介意 我们借他的衣服穿穿的
Anyway, if you think about it logically,
何况，换个角度想，理论上来说...
we're not even taking them out of the wardrobe.
我们甚至没有把它们带出衣橱呢
- But that's a girl's coat! - I know.
- 这可是女孩儿的大衣啊！ - 我知道
...lots and lots of lovely food, and we'll have lots and lots of...
...好多好多好吃的 我们还可以...
Lu?
露西？
Lucy!
露西！
Who would do something like this?
谁会这么做呢？！
"The Faun Tumnus is hereby charged
“奉纳尼亚女王的旨意...
with High Treason against Her lmperial Majesty,
半人羊汤姆那斯因违反纳尼亚律法...
Jadis, Queen of Narnia,
...通敌和包庇人类...
for comforting her enemies and fraternizing with humans.
...而予以就地逮捕！
Signed Maugrim, Captain of the Secret Police.
秘密警察首领毛戈里姆...
Long Live the Queen."
...女王万岁！”
All right. Now we really should go back.
好啦， 这下我们可真得回去了
But what about Mr. Tumnus?
可汤姆那斯先生又怎么办呢？
If he was arrested just for being with a human,
如果他是因为和人类有接触而被捕
- I don't think there's much we can do. - You don't understand, do you?
- ...我们也无能为力 - 你们还没意识到吗？
I'm the human.
我就是那个“人类”
She must have found out he helped me.
她一定是发现 他曾经帮助过我
- Maybe we could call the police. - These are the police.
- 或许我们可以请警察来帮忙 - 那些就是警察
Don't worry, Lu. We'll think of something.
别担心，露西 我们再想点儿其他办法
Why?
为什么？
I mean, he's a criminal.
我是说...他是个罪犯
Did that bird just "psst" us?
刚才是不是那头鸟在轻唤我们？
Lt... It's a beaver.
这...是头海狸
Here, boy.
过来，小东西
I ain't gonna smell it, if that's what you want.
如果你是故意想逗我玩儿 我才不想闻你的手呢
Sorry.
对不起
Lucy Pevensie?
露西・佩文西？
Yes?
是我...
That's the hankie I gave to Mr. Tum...
嘿，那条手绢是我之前送给T...
Tumnus. He got it to me just before they took him.
汤姆那斯 他在被捕之前把它交给了我
Is he all right?
他没事吧？
Further in.
跟我来
- What are you doing? - She's right.
- 你们要做什么？ - 她说得对
How do we know we can trust him?
我们凭什么相信他呢？
He said he knows the faun.
他说他知道半人羊的下落
He's a beaver. He shouldn't be saying anything!
那只不过是头海狸， 他能开口讲话就已经好奇怪了！
Everything all right?
有什么问题吗？
Yes. We were just talking.
对，我们正在讨论呢
That's better left for safer quarters.
那也最好找个安全的地方
He means the trees.
他是说，树有耳朵呢...
Come on. We don't want to be caught out here after nightfall.
快来 大家都不愿意在夜幕来临前被逮住吧
Blimey! Looks like the old girl has got the kettle on.
哎，真要命！ 看来她已经开始做饭了...
Nice cup o' Rosy Lee.
这儿就是...玫瑰的小窝！
- It's lovely. - It's merely a trifle.
- 真可爱！ - 这只是雏形...
Still plenty to do. Ain't quite finished it yet.
有很多地方还不尽如人意 需要添加和修整...
It'll look the business when it is, though.
不过，我相信最后的样子 会让大家大为惊叹的！
Beaver, is that you? I've been worried sick!
是你回来了吗？ 我好担心啊！
If I find you've been out with Badger again, I...
要是再让我发现你和袋狸在一块儿 我就...
Well, those aren't badgers.
喔，原来不是袋狸！
Oh, I never thought I'd live to see this day.
噢，真没想到 我居然还能盼到这天
Look at my fur. You couldn't give me ten minutes warning?
你也真是的，我的皮毛这么乱 有贵客来，也不提早通知我一声...
I'd have given a week if I thought it would've helped.
要是他们愿意等 给你一周的时间都行！
and some civilized company.
好好款待款待你们 尽尽地主之谊
Now, careful. Watch your step.
喔，小心，别碰着头了
Excuse the mess.
不好意思，家里乱糟糟的
Can't get Mr. Beaver to get out of his chair.
这家伙总是懒得做家务
Enjoyin' the scenery, are we?
景色很美吧？
Isn't there anything we can do to help Tumnus?
我们可以做些什么 来帮助汤姆那斯呢？
They'll have taken him to the Witch's. You know what they say.
就像逮捕令中说的 他们会把他带到白巫婆那里去
There's few that go through them gates that come out again.
而凡是进那了扇门的 没几个能活着出来
Fish 'n' chips?
来点儿鱼片干吧？
But there is hope, dear. Lots of hope.
不过还不是完全没希望，亲爱的 乐观点儿吧
Oh, yeah, there's a right bit more than hope!
噢，当然 总会有办法解决的嘛！
Aslan is on the move.
阿斯兰正在采取行动呢
Who's Aslan?
谁是阿斯兰？
You cheeky little blighter.
你们可真会开玩笑
What?
怎么？
- You don't know, do you? - We haven't exactly been here long.
- You don't know, do you? - 你们真不知道？ - 我们在这儿还没呆多久呢
Well, he's only the king of the whole wood.
喔，在我们眼中 他是不可替代的森林之王...
The top geezer. The real King of Narnia.
...一位睿智的老人 纳尼亚真正的统治者
- He's been away for a long while. - But he's just got back!
- 之前，他离开了许久... - 不过，终于他又回来了！
And he's waitin' for you near the Stone Table!
而且，他正在神器石桌附近 等待着你们！
- He's waiting for us? - You're bloomin' joking!
- 他在等待我们？ - 你们是在开玩笑吧？！
They don't even know about the prophecy!
他们甚至连那则传说中的 预言都没听说过！
- Well, then... - Look.
- 喔，那么.. - 听我说
Aslan's return,
阿斯兰的归来...
Tumnus' arrest, the secret police,
汤姆那斯的被捕，秘密警察的介入
it's all happening because of you!
这一切，都是因为你们的出现！
- You're blaming us? - No! Not blaming.
- 那么，你...是在责备我们么？ - 不！不是在责备你们...
- Thanking you. - There's a prophecy.
- ...反而，我们要感谢你们！ - 传说中，有一则预言...
"When Adam's flesh and Adam's bone
“当由亚当赋予生命的血肉之躯...
sits at Cair Paravel in throne,
坐上卡尔的宝座之时...
the evil time will be over and done."
...那罪恶统治的时代将就此终结！”
- That doesn't really rhyme. - I know it don't.
- 那听起来可不怎么押韵喔 - ...没错，可是...
You're kinda missin' the point!
这不是问题的关键！
It has long been foretold
长久以来 还流传着这样的说法...
that two Sons of Adam and two Daughters of Eve
在两位“亚当之子”和 两位“夏娃之女”的带领下...
will defeat the White Witch and restore peace to Narnia.
大家会推翻白巫婆的罪恶统治 重新把和平的种子撒播在纳尼亚的土地上！
And you think we're the ones?
而你们认为我们就是传说中的人物？
You'd better be, 'cause Aslan's already fitted out your army.
最好就是你们... 因为阿斯兰已经为你们募集了军队
- Our army? - Mum sent us away
- 我们的军队？ - 妈妈送走的目的...
so we wouldn't get caught up in a war.
就是特意安排 让我们远离战争
I think you've made a mistake.
我想你们一定弄错了
- We're not heroes. - We're from Finchley.
- 我们并不是你们传说中的英雄 - 我们只是四个来自芬赤雷的孩子
Thank you for your hospitality.
谢谢你们的款待
- But we really have to go. - No, you can't just leave!
- 可我们真得走了 - 不，你们不能就这么离开！
He's right. We have to help Mr. Tumnus.
他说得对 我们得帮助汤姆那斯先生
It's out of our hands.
这不是我们力所能及的
I'm sorry,
我很抱歉...
but it's time the four of us were getting home. Ed?
可我们真的得回去了 爱德蒙？
- I'm gonna kill him. - You may not have to.
- 我真想拧死了那小子！ - 先别急
Has Edmund ever been to Narnia before?
爱德蒙之前曾来过纳尼亚吗？
Hurry!
快点儿！
- Edmund! - They'll hear you!
- 爱德蒙！ - 嘘，他们会听到的！
No!
不！
- Get off! - You're playing into her hands.
- 放开我！ - 这里是她的地盘，别拿自己的生命开玩笑！
- We can't just let him go! - He's our brother!
- 我们不能就这样让他离开！ - 他是我们的亲人！
He's the bait! The Witch wants all four of you!
他只是白巫婆的诱饵！ 把你们四个全弄到手才是她的真正目的！
- Why? - To stop the prophecy from coming true.
- 为什么？ - 为了防止预言中的故事变成现实！
To kill you!
她会杀了你们的！
- This is all your fault. - My fault?
- 这都是你的错 - 我的错？
None of this would have happened if you had listened to me!
要是当初你听我的早些离开 就不会发生这样的事了！
- You knew this would happen. - I didn't know.
- 难道你当初就知道事情会变成这样么？！ - 我当然不知道！
Which is why we should have left while we could!
正因为这样 我那时才建议赶快离开这鬼地方！
Stop it!
别吵了！
- This isn't going to help Edmund. - She's right.
- 争吵是无济于事的！ - 她说得对
Only Aslan can help your brother now.
现在只有阿斯兰才能帮助你们的兄弟
Then take us to him.
那就带我们去见他
Be still, stranger, or you'll never move again.
别动，陌生人 否则就要你的命！
- Who are you? - I'm Edmund!
- 你是谁？ - 我是爱德蒙！
I met the Queen in the woods! She told me to come back here!
我曾在林子里见过女王 失她让我到这儿来找她的！
I'm a Son of Adam!
我是亚当之子！
Or else, not so fortunate.
...也或者，不是什么好事..
Right this way.
这边 这边走
Wait here.
在这里等着 在这儿等一会儿
Like it?
喜欢这样？ 喜欢吗？
I thought you might.
我想你可以... 我就想你会喜欢的
Tell me, Edmund...
告诉我 告诉我，爱德蒙...
Are your sisters deaf?
你的姐妹是聋子吗？？？ 你的姐妹们耳朵不好使吗？
No.
不是... 没有啊...
And your brother, is he...
还有你的哥哥，他... 那么，你的哥哥，他是否...
...unintelligent?
是弱智吗？？？ 是个无知的小傻瓜？
Well, I think so. But Mum says...
哦，我认为是的。。。 但妈妈说。。。
Then how dare you come alone?!
那么你竟敢自己一个人来？！
- I tried! - Edmund, I asked so little of you.
我试过了！ 我只让你做这一点点事情
- They just don't listen to me! - You couldn't even do that.
他们不听我的！ 你都办不到
I did bring them halfway.
我已经把他们带到附近了
They're at the little house at the dam with the Beavers.
他们和海狸们在水坝旁边的小房子里
Well.
好
I suppose you're not a total loss then, are you?
那你也不是一无是处嘛...
Well, I was wondering,
那么，我在想
could I maybe have some more Turkish delight now?
你能再给我一些土耳其点心吗？
Our guest is hungry.
我们的客人饿了
This way for your num-nums.
这边请去吃你的大餐
You know what to do.
你知道该怎么做
Hurry, Mother! They're after us!
快点，妈妈！他们在追我们
- Oh, right then. - What's she doing?
哦，好的 她在干什么？
Oh, you'll be thanking me later.
哦，你回头会感谢我的
It's a long journey and Beaver gets pretty cranky when he's hungry.
这会是一个相当长的旅途，而且海狸在饿的时候 会变得很暴躁的
I'm cranky now!
我现在已经很暴躁了！
Take them.
抓住他们
- Do you think we'll need jam? - Only if the Witch serves toast.
你认为我们现在需要酱吗？ 只有在巫婆给我们准备晚宴的时候
Hurry.
快点
Badger and me dug this. Comes out right near his place.
獾和我一起挖的这个 出口在他的住所附近
You told me it led to your mum's!
你告诉我这个是通到你妈妈那里的！
Lucy!
露西!
They're in the tunnel.
他们在地道里
- Quick! This way. - Hurry!
快，这边！ 快点！
- Run! - Quick! Quick! Quick!
快跑！ 快！快！快！
You should have brought a map!
你应该带一张地图！
There wasn't room next to the jam.
把酱带上了就没地方放地图了
Come on, Lucy!
快点！
I'm so sorry, dear.
我非常抱歉，亲爱的
He was my best mate.
他是我最好的朋友
What happened here?
这里发生什么了？
This is what becomes of those who cross the Witch.
这就是背叛巫婆的下场
You take one more step, traitor, and I'll chew you to splinters!
你变得更坏了，叛徒 我会把你咬成碎片！
Relax. I'm one of the good guys.
放松点，我是好人
Yeah? Well, you look an awful lot like one of the bad ones.
你？哼，你更像是个罪大恶极的人
An unfortunate family resemblance.
这就是你们这个家庭的不幸
But we can argue breeding later. Right now we've got to move.
我们晚一点再讨论教育的问题吧 现在我们必须得走了
What did you have in mind?
你到底想干什么？
Greetings, gents.
各位好啊
- Lost something, have we? - Don't patronize me!
我们似乎错过了什么 别那样跟我说话！
I know where your allegiance lies.
我知道你跟谁是一伙的
We're looking for some humans.
我们在找一些人类
Humans? Here in Narnia?
人类？在这里？
That's a valuable bit of information, don't you think?
那可是有点价值的信息啊，你不这么认为吗？
Your reward is your life.
给你的奖赏就是你的命
It's not much,
不算多
but still.
虽然如此...
Where are the fugitives?
还是快告诉我那些人类在哪里？
North. They ran north.
北边，他们往北边跑了
Smell them out.
把他们找出来
They were helping Tumnus. The Witch got here before I did.
那些獾帮助过 巫婆比我更早到这里
Are you all right?
你还好吧？
Well, I wish I could say their bark was worse than their bite.
啊，我真希望他们的叫声能比他们的牙齿更恐怖
Stop squirming! You're worse than Beaver on bath day.
别乱动 你要洗澡的时候会比海狸更糟糕
Worst day of the year.
这一年中最糟糕的一天
Thank you for your kindness,
感谢你们的热情款待
but that's all the cure I have time for.
但是这伤是需要时间来治愈的
You're leaving?
你现在要走吗？
It has been a pleasure, My Queen, and an honor, but time is short
我的皇后，跟您在一起是一种快乐，更是一种荣誉 不过时间是短暂的
and Aslan himself has asked me to gather more troops.
而且他让我去征召更多的部队
- You've seen Aslan? - What's he like?
你已经见到他了？ 他怎么样？
Like everything we've ever heard.
想我们大家所听到的一样
You'll be glad to have him by your side in the battle against the Witch.
你们会非常高兴和他一起跟巫婆战斗的
But we're not planning on fighting any witch.
但我们并不打算和什么巫婆战斗
But surely, King Peter, the prophecy!
但那则预言让我们一起战斗
We can't go to war without you.
我们不能没有你们
We just want our brother back.
但我们只想救回我们的兄弟
Lf...
如果...
If you're not going to eat that...
如果你不想吃那个的话，能不能给我...
I'd get up, but...
我想站起来，但...
...but my legs.
但我的腿
Mr. Tumnus.
汤姆那斯先生
What's left of him.
正是我
- You're Lucy Pevensie's brother. - I'm Edmund.
你是她的哥哥 我是
Yes. Yes, you have the same nose.
是的，你们有着一样的鼻子
Is your sister all right?
你的妹妹还好吗？
Is she safe?
她现在安全吗？
I don't know.
我不知道
My police tore that dam apart.
我的警察们已经把那个水坝翻了个底朝天
Your little family are nowhere to be found.
但你那个小小的家庭却不见踪影
- Where did they go? - I don't know!
他们哪儿去了？ 我不知道！
Then you're of no further use to me.
那么，你已经没什么用了
Wait! The beaver said something about Aslan!
等一下！海狸说了一些有关他的事情
Aslan?
他？
Where?
他在哪里？
- I... - He's a stranger here, Your Majesty.
我... 他在这里这是个陌生人，陛下。
He can't be expected to know anything.
他不会知道什么事情的
I said... where is Aslan?
我在问你... 他在哪里？
I... I don't know.
我...我真的不知道
I left before they said anything.
在他们说那些事情之前，我已经离开了
I wanted to see you!
因为我想见到您！
Guard!
警卫！
Your Majesty.
陛下
Release the faun.
把那个半人马放了
Do you know why you're here, faun?
Do you know why you're here, faun? 你知道你为什么会在这里吗？
Because I believe in a free Narnia.
因为我坚信一个自由的纳尼亚会到来的
You're here...
你在这里...
...because he turned you in.
...是因为他出卖了你
For sweeties.
为了一些糖果
Take him upstairs.
把他带到楼上
And ready my sleigh.
准备好我的雪橇
Edmund misses his family.
他想他的家人了
Now, Aslan's camp is near the Stone Table
他现在的宿营地在石桌附近
- just across the frozen river. - River?
就是过了这条冰冻的河 河？
The river's been frozen solid for a hundred years.
这条河已经冰冻了一百年了
- It's so far. - It's the world, dear.
好远啊 亲爱的，这可是个世界
Did you expect it to be small?
你认为一个世界会很小吗？
Smaller.
只希望小一点
When you're ready, Son of Adam.
你准备好了吗，亚当的儿子
Come on, humans! While we're still young.
快点，人类们！ 当我们还年轻的时候
If he tells us to hurry one more time,
如果他再叫我们快一点
I'm gonna turn him into a big, fluffy hat.
我会把他变成一个大绒毛帽子
Hurry up! Come on!
快点！跟上！
- He is getting a little bossy. - No! Behind you! It's her!
他似乎变得有点专横了 她在你们的后边！
- Run! Run! - Run!
快跑！快！快！
Hurry!
快啊！
Inside!
快进去！
Dive! Dive!
快钻进去！快！
Quick! Quick, quick, quick!
快！快，快，快！
Maybe she's gone.
也许她已经走了
- I suppose I'll go look. - No!
我觉得我应该出去看看 不！
You're worth nothing to Narnia dead.
如果你死了，就没救了
Well, neither are you, Beaver.
你也不能死啊，海狸
Thanks, sweetheart.
谢谢你，亲爱的
What's that? What's?
那是什么声音？那是。。。 嘘，嘘，嘘
Come out! Come out!
出来！都出来！
I hope you've all been good 'cause there's someone here to see you!
我希望你们都毫发无伤，因为这里有某个人想见 你们！
Merry Christmas, sir.
圣诞快乐，先生
It certainly is, Lucy, since you have arrived.
自从你们到了这里，我一直很快乐
Look, I've put up with a lot since I got here, but this...
自从我到了这里，我已经看到了很多新的东西， 但这次...
- We thought you were the Witch. - Yes, yes, I'm sorry about that,
我们以为你是那个巫婆 是，是，很对不起让你们误会了
but in my defense, I have been driving one of these longer than the Witch.
但实际上我的马车要比巫婆的长
I thought there was no Christmas in Narnia.
我记得纳尼亚这里没有圣诞节
No. Not for a long time.
是的，很久都没有了
But the hope that you have brought, Your Majesties,
但你们给我们带来了希望，尊敬的各位
is finally starting to weaken the Witch's power.
你们的到来减弱了巫婆的法力
Still, I dare say you could do with these.
还有，我相信这些东西会让你们高兴的
The juice of the fire-flower.
这是火焰花的果汁
One drop will cure any injury.
一滴就可以治愈任何的创伤
And though I hope you never have to use it...
虽然我希望你们永远都用不到这个
Thank you, sir,
谢谢你，先生
but I think I could be brave enough.
但我认为我会变得很勇敢的
I'm sure you could.
我相信你会的
But battles are ugly affairs.
但战斗是丑陋的事情
Susan.
苏珊
Trust in this bow and it will not easily miss.
相信这把弓，它就不会让你失望的
What happened to "battles are ugly affairs"?
但战斗是丑陋的事情啊？
Though you don't seem to have a problem making yourself heard,
虽然你看起来并不需要这个
blow on this and wherever you are,
但你不论何时何地吹响这个
help will come.
都会有人来帮助你的
Thanks.
谢谢
Peter.
彼得
The time to use these may be near at hand.
你马上就要用到这些了
Thank you, sir.
谢谢你，先生
These are tools, not toys.
这些是战斗的武器，不是玩具
Bear them well and wisely.
把它们带好并且学会聪明的使用它们
Now, I must be off.
现在，我必须走了
Winter is almost over,
冬天快要结束了
and things do pile up when you've been gone a hundred years.
而且在我不在的这一百年了，堆积了一大堆我要 做的事情
Long live Aslan!
阿斯兰万岁！
And Merry Christmas!
圣诞快乐！
- See you next year! - Goodbye!
明年再见！ 再见！
Told you he was real.
我告诉你他是真实存在的吧
He said winter was almost over.
他说冬天就要过去了
You know what that means.
你们那是什么意思吗？
No more ice.
没有冰了
- We need to cross, now! - Don't beavers make dams?
我们现在必须过河！ 海狸不造水坝吗？
- I'm not that fast, dear. - Come on!
亲爱的，我想我游不了那么快 快！
Wait! Will you think about this for a minute?
等一下！你们不再好好想一想了吗？
- We don't have a minute. - I'm just trying to be realistic.
我们已经没有时间了 我只是想让你们现实一点
No, you're trying to be smart. As usual.
不，你只是想像平常一样显得聪明一点罢了
Wait. Maybe I should go first.
等一下，也许我应该先探探
Maybe you should.
我想你是对的
You've been sneaking second helpings, haven't you?
我想你是需要我的帮助，对吗？
Well, you never know which meal's gonna be your last.
你永远不知道哪一顿饭是你的最后一餐，
Especially with your cooking.
特别是你做的饭
If Mum knew what we were doing...
如果妈妈知道我们现在做的事
Mum's not here.
妈妈不在这里
Oh, no!
欧，不！
Run!
快跑！
Hurry!
快一点！
Put that down, boy.
孩子，把那把剑放下
- Someone could get hurt. - Don't worry about me!
否则有人会受伤的 别担心我！
Run him through!
快杀死他！
Leave now while you can, and your brother leaves with you.
你们如果现在想离开他的话，我会让你们的 兄弟跟你们一起离开的
Stop, Peter! Maybe we should listen to him!
把剑放下，彼得！ 也许我们应该听他的！
Smart girl.
真是个聪明的女孩
Don't listen to him! Kill him! Kill him now!
不要听他的！ 杀死他！现在就杀死他！
Oh, come on. This isn't your war.
欧，不要这样，这不是属于你们的战争
All my Queen wants is for you to take your family and go.
我们的皇后只是想你和你的家人一起离开
Look, just because some man in a red coat hands you a sword,
你不要以为那个穿红夜的圣诞老人给了你一把剑
it doesn't make you a hero! Just drop it!
你就变成了英雄！ 快把剑放下！
No, Peter! Narnia needs you!
不，彼得！ 需要你！
Gut him while you still have a chance!
在你还有机会的时候快杀了他！
What's it gonna be, Son of Adam? I won't wait forever.
你想怎么样，亚当的儿子？ 我不能像这样永远等下去
And neither will the river.
这条河也不能等了
Peter!
彼得！
Hold onto me!
快抓紧我！
What have you done?
你做了什么？
Lucy!
露西！
Has anyone seen my coat?
有谁看到我的衣服了吗？
Don't you worry, dear.
别担心，亲爱的
Your brother's got you well looked after.
你的哥哥照顾的你很周到的
And I don't think you'll be needing those coats anymore.
而且我认为你们不再需要那些冬装了
It's so warm out.
这里好热啊
I'll go and check the sleigh.
哦，我现在去检查一下雪橇
Your Majesty.
尊敬的陛下
We found the traitor. He was rallying your enemies near the Shuddering Woods.
我们发现了这个叛徒
You were so helpful to my wolves last night.
你昨晚对我的狼群帮助很大啊
Perhaps you can help me now.
也许你现在能帮助我
- Forgive me, Your Majesty. - Oh, don't waste time with flattery.
原谅我，陛下 哦，别浪费时间在这些奉承上
Not to seem rude, but I wasn't actually talking to you.
这也许不算是很粗鲁 但我没有在跟你讲话
Where are the humans headed?
那些人类去了哪里？
Wait! No! Don't. The beaver said something about the Stone Table,
等一下！不要这样！海狸说了一些关于石桌的事情
and that Aslan had an army there.
而且他们还说阿斯兰在那里有一支军队
An army?
一支军队？
Thank you, Edmund.
谢谢你，爱德蒙
I'm glad this creature got to see some honesty...
我很高兴这个生物还能看到诚实...
...before he dies. - No!
...在他死之前！ 不要！
Think about whose side you're on, Edmund.
好好想想你是站在哪一边的，爱德蒙
Mine...
我这一边...
...or theirs.
...还是他们这一边
Go on ahead. Gather the faithful.
快点去 召集我的部队
If it's a war Aslan wants...
如果这是一场阿斯兰向往的战争...
...it's a war he shall get.
...那么我会让这场战争变成现实
Why are they all staring at us?
他们为什么都盯着我们看？
Maybe they think you look funny.
也许他们认为你长得很奇怪
Stop your fussing. You look lovely.
哦，别乱挠了 你看起来已经很好了
We have come to see Aslan.
我们要见阿斯兰
Welcome, Peter, Son of Adam.
欢迎你，彼得，亚当的儿子
Welcome, Susan and Lucy, Daughters of Eve.
欢迎你们，苏珊和露西，夏娃的女儿们
And welcome to you, Beavers. You have my thanks.
还有欢迎你们，海狸们 我非常感谢你们
But where is the fourth?
但另外一个哪儿去了？
That's why we're here, sir.
这就是我们来这儿的原因
We need your help.
我们需要您的帮助
We had a little trouble along the way.
我们在路上遇到了点小麻烦
Our brother's been captured by the White Witch.
我们的兄弟被白巫婆给抓走了
Captured? How could this happen?
抓走了？这怎么可能？
He betrayed them, Your Majesty.
他背叛了他们，陛下
- Then he has betrayed us all! - Peace, Oreius.
那么他背叛了我们所有人！ 安静，奥利斯
I'm sure there's an explanation.
我敢肯定他们会解释清楚的
It's my fault, really.
都是我的错
I was too hard on him.
我对他太苛刻了
We all were.
我们都有责任
Sir, he's our brother.
先生，他是我们的兄弟
I know, dear one.
我知道，亲爱的
But that only makes the betrayal all the worse.
但这样的背叛更让人无法容忍
This may be harder than you think.
事情可能不像你们想象的那么简单
That is Cair Paravel, the castle of the four thrones.
这里是卡尔 四帝之城
In one of which you will sit, Peter, as High King.
你会成为其中的王中之王，彼得
You doubt the prophecy?
你怀疑那个预言吗？
No. That's just it.
不，我坚信...
Aslan, I'm not what you all think I am.
阿斯兰，我不像你想象的那样强大
Peter Pevensie, formerly of Finchley.
彼得・佩文西，你原来是来自芬赤雷
Beaver also mentioned that you planned on turning him into a hat.
海狸还告诉我你曾经想把他变成一顶帽子
Peter, there is a Deep Magic,
彼得，这世界上有一种超级魔法
more powerful than any of us,
比我们任何一个都要强大
that rules over all of Narnia.
它统治着纳尼亚的所有
It defines right from wrong,
它决定着事物的是是非非
and governs all our destinies.
并且决定着我们每个人的命运
Yours... and mine.
你们的...还有我的
But I couldn't even protect my own family.
但我连自己的家人都保护不了
You've brought them safely this far.
你已经把他们安全的带到了这么远的地方
Not all of them.
但并不是每一个人都来到了这里
Peter, I will do what I can to help your brother,
彼得，我会尽力救出你们的兄弟的
but I need you to consider what I ask of you.
但我需要你考虑我跟你讲过的话
I, too, want my family safe.
我也为我的家庭着想
Is our little prince uncomfortable?
我们的小王子不舒服吗？
Does he want his pillow fluffed?
要松软的枕头吗？
Special treatment for the special boy!
特殊的人就要特别对待
Isn't that what you wanted?
这不就是你想要得吗？
You look like Mum.
你看上去像妈妈
Mum hasn't had a dress like this since before the war.
战争以后妈妈就没穿过这样的裙子了
We should bring her one back. A whole trunk full!
我们应该给她带一整箱回去
If we ever get back.
如果我们能回的去
I'm sorry I'm like that.
刚才不好意思
We used to have fun together, didn't we?
我们曾经在一起感到很快乐，对吗？
Yes. Before you got boring.
对，直到你感到无聊
Oh, really?
是吗？
Please don't try to run.
你哪儿也别想去
- We're tired. - And we prefer to kill you quickly.
- 我们很累了 - 所以要速战速决
Get back!
回来！
Peter!
彼得！
Come on.
快
We've already been through this before.
我们已经这样来过一次了
We both know you haven't got it in you.
我们都知道你并没有什么本事
Peter! Watch out!
彼得！小心！
No! Stay your weapons. This is Peter's battle.
不！ 这是彼得的战役
You may think you're a king,
你也许认为你是国王
but you're going to die...
但你就要死了...
...like a dog! - Look out!
- 像一头狗一样 - 小心
Peter!
彼得！
He'll lead you to Edmund.
他会带你们找到爱德蒙
Peter.
彼得
Clean your sword.
擦干你的剑
Rise, Sir Peter Wolf's-Bane,
起身
Knight of Narnia.
纳尼亚之王
The minotaurs will take the left flanks.
牛头怪从左侧进攻
We'll keep the giants in reserve and send dwarfs in first.
巨人预留在后面，矮子打前阵
The prisoner!
囚犯逃走了！
You're not going to kill me?
不要杀我
Not yet.
暂时不会
We have work to do.
我们还有事做
Edmund!
爱德蒙！
What's done is done.
以前的事就让它们过去吧... 已经无法挽回了
There is no need to speak to Edmund about what is past.
不必再提了
Hello.
喂
- Are you all right? - I'm a little tired.
- 你没事吧？ - 就是有点累
Get some sleep.
睡会儿吧
And Edmund...
爱德蒙...
...try not to wander off.
不要到处乱走
Narnia's not going to run out of toast, Ed.
纳尼亚从缺烤面包，爱德蒙
I'm sure they'll pack something up for the journey back.
走时他们一定会为你们打包好的
We're going home?
我们要离开？
You are.
你们
I promised Mum I'd keep you three safe.
我想妈妈会保证你们的安全
But it doesn't mean I can't stay behind and help.
但我还是可以留下帮忙的
But they need us.
可他们需要我们
All four of us.
我们四个
Lucy, it's too dangerous.
露西，拿太危险了
You almost drowned! Edmund was almost killed!
你差点儿就杯淹死了！ 而爱德蒙也差点儿就没命了！
Which is why we have to stay.
也正是以为如此我们才要留下
I've seen what the White Witch can do. And I've helped her do it.
我知道白巫婆的能力
And we can't leave these people behind to suffer for it.
我们不能让这些无辜的人受苦
I suppose that's it then.
就这么定了
Where are you going?
你去哪儿？
To get in some practice.
练习一下
Come on, Ed! Sword point up, like Oreius showed us.
爱德蒙！举起剑来，像奥利斯教的那样
- En garde! - Now block.
- 接招！ - 挡住！
- Hey! - Peter! Edmund!
- 嘿！ - 彼德！爱德蒙！
My name is Philip.
- 我叫菲利 - 噢...
Sorry.
对不起
The Witch has demanded a meeting with Aslan.
巫婆要求会晤阿斯兰
She's on her way here.
她已经在来的路上了
Jadis, the Queen of Narnia!
纳尼亚女皇！
- Go away, Witch! - Empress of the Lone Islands!
- 快滚蛋，巫婆！ - 孤岛之王...
You don't belong here! Go away!
你不属于这里！
You have a traitor in your midst, Aslan.
你们阵营中有叛徒，阿斯兰
His offense was not against you.
尽管他并没有背叛你
Have you forgotten the laws upon which Narnia was built?
你忘记纳尼亚律法了吗？
Do not cite the Deep Magic to me, Witch.
不要和我提那亘古的魔咒，巫师
I was there when it was written.
制定它的时候，我也在场
Then you'll remember well that every traitor belongs to me.
那你就应该清楚， 凡是叛徒...都是我的人
His blood is my property.
他的血液是我的“财富”！
Try and take him then.
那就得看你有没有能耐抢走他了
Do you really think that mere force will deny me my right...
你真认为纯粹的武力可以让我屈服吗....
...little King?
...小王子？
Aslan knows that unless I have blood, as the law demands,
阿斯兰知道除非我拥有他的血液，
all of Narnia will be overturned
否则纳尼亚就会毁灭
and perish in fire and water.
...在烈火和洪水中消亡
That boy will die
那个男孩注定该...
on the Stone Table...
在那石桌上接受死亡的惩罚
...as is tradition.
这就是我们的传统
You dare not refuse me.
你胆敢违抗传统，来拒绝我么
Enough.
够了
I shall talk with you alone.
我要和你单独谈谈
She has renounced her claim on the Son of Adam's blood.
她放弃了攫取亚当之子血液的意图
How do I know your promise will be kept?
叫我如何相信， 你会遵守刚才的诺言呢？
Susan!
- 苏珊！ - 嗯？
Shouldn't you both be in bed?
你们早该睡了
We couldn't sleep.
我们睡不着
Please, Aslan.
求求你，阿斯兰
Couldn't we come with you?
我们不能和你一块儿去吗？
I would be glad of the company for a while.
我很高兴你们可以陪伴我一程
Thank you.
谢谢
It is time.
就到这儿吧
From here, I must go on alone.
我必须自己走了
But Aslan...
可是，阿斯兰...
You have to trust me. For this must be done.
相信我... 这是无法逃避的
Thank you, Susan.
谢谢，苏珊
Thank you, Lucy.
谢谢，露西
And farewell.
再会
Behold. The great lion.
停步，伟大的雄狮
Do you want some milk?
要喝奶吗？
Why doesn't he fight back?
他为什么不还手？
Bind him!
把它绑起来！
Tie him up! Get him!
绑起来！
Let him first be shaved.
先把他的毛给剃了！
Bring him to me.
带到我这边来
You know, Aslan,
要知道，阿斯兰
I'm a little disappointed in you.
我对你有点儿失望
Did you honestly think by all this that you could save the human traitor?
你真地认为你的牺牲 可以挽救那个人类叛徒吗？
You are giving me your life
即使把你的生命给了我...
and saving no one.
也无济于事！
So much for love.
爱的代价太大了
Tonight...
就在今夜...
...the Deep Magic will be appeased!
让亘古的魔咒释放吧！
But tomorrow,
明天...
we will take Narnia
纳尼亚就是我们的了
forever!
期限是...永远！
In that knowledge,
就是说...
despair...
今后的世界， 会充满失望...
...and die!
...和死亡！
The Great Cat...
伟大的“猫儿”...
...is dead!
接受死亡的洗礼吧！
General.
将军！
Prepare your troops for battle.
准备战斗
However short it may be.
不管差距有多悬殊
It's too late.
太晚了...
He's gone.
他去世了...
He must have known what he was doing.
他当时一定十分清醒
Get away! Get away, all of you!
一边去！一边去！
No. Look.
不
We have to tell the others.
我们应该告诉其他人
- We can't just leave him! - Lucy, there's no time.
- 我们不能就这样把他扔在这里 - 露西，时间不多了
They need to know.
一定要让他们知道
The trees.
...树木精灵
Be still, my Princes.
我的王子，别着急
I bring grave news from your sisters.
我从你们姐妹那里 带来了沉痛的消息
She's right.
她是对的
He's gone.
他走了
Then you'll have to lead us.
那就由您来领导我们
Peter, there's an army out there and it's ready to follow you.
彼得，我们所有人都愿意 跟随你走上战场！
- I can't. - Aslan believed you could.
- 我恐怕不行 - 既然阿斯兰相信你...
And so do I.
那么我也是
The Witch's army is nearing, sire. What are your orders?
巫师的军队已经越来越近了， 您有什么指令吗？
They come, Your Highness, in numbers and weapons far greater than our own.
他们的人和武器数量都远胜我们
Numbers do not win a battle.
数量决定不了成败
No. But I bet they help.
至少那很有用...
I have no interest in prisoners.
我对活着的没兴趣
Kill them all.
...斩尽杀绝！
Look to the sky!
往天上看！
Are you with me?
准备好了吗？
To the death.
至死不渝
For Narnia and for Aslan!
为了纳尼亚和阿斯兰！
Go!
冲啊！
Go! For Aslan!
冲啊！为了阿斯兰！
We should go.
我们该走了
I'm so cold.
我觉得很冷
Susan!
苏珊！
Where's Aslan?
阿斯兰在那里？
What have they done?
他们干了什么？
Aslan!
阿斯兰！
But we saw the knife. The Witch.
可我们昨夜亲眼看见她杀了你
If the Witch knew the true meaning of sacrifice,
如果巫师了解牺牲的真正含义
she might have interpreted the Deep Magic differently.
她就会从不同的角度理解亘古魔咒了
That when a willing victim who has committed no treachery
如果把一个无辜的人...
is killed in a traitor's stead,
当作叛徒处死
the Stone Table will crack
石桌就会崩裂
and even death itself will turn backwards.
而死亡也会被逆转
We sent the news that you were dead.
我们已经发出你死亡的消息了
Peter and Edmund will have gone to war.
彼得和爱德蒙将奔赴沙场
We have to help them.
我们得要去帮助他们
We will, dear one, but not alone.
当然，亲爱的， 我们一起走
Climb on my back.
骑上来
We have far to go and little time to get there.
我们的时间很紧
And you may want to cover your ears.
你们捂住耳朵
Fire!
开火！
Yes!
好的！
Fall back! Draw them to the rocks!
后退！把他们引到石堆里来！
Where are we going?
我们去哪里？
Hang on!
抓紧！
Fall back!
退！
Go on, fall back!
退回来！
Stop!
停！
Susan, this is...
苏珊，这是...
Mr. Tumnus!
汤姆那斯先生！
Come, we must hurry and search the castle.
来，我们必须赶快搜索一下这里
Peter will need everyone we can find.
彼得需要我们找到的所有人
Edmund! There's too many!
爱德蒙！人太多了！
Get out of here!
快跑吧！
Get the girls and get them home!
带露西他们回家！
You heard him! Let's go!
快走！
Peter said get out of here!
彼得说快跑！
Peter's not king yet.
彼得还不是国王
Impossible!
不可能！
It is finished.
结束了
- Peter!
- 彼得！
Where's Edmund?
爱德蒙在哪里？
Edmund!
爱德蒙！
When are you gonna learn to do as you're told?
什么时候你才能好好听我的话呢？
To the glistening Eastern Sea,
象征着美丽的东部海洋...
I give you Queen Lucy, the Valiant.
您是我们勇敢的露西女皇
To the great Western Wood,
象征着伟大的西部森林...
King Edmund, the Just.
我赐予你，公正的爱德蒙国王称号
To the radiant Southern Sun,
象征着耀眼的南部骄阳...
Queen Susan, the Gentle.
苏珊女皇温柔而品格坚韧
And to the clear Northern Sky,
象征着晴朗的北部天际
I give you King Peter,
我封你为...
the Magnificent.
伟大的彼得国王
Once a King or Queen of Narnia,
一日为纳尼亚之帝
always a King or Queen.
终生为纳尼亚之王
until the stars rain down from the heavens.
直到星星坠落天堂...
Long live King Peter!
彼得万岁！
Long live King Edmund!
爱德蒙万岁！
Long live Queen Susan!
苏珊万岁！
Long live Queen Lucy!
露西万岁！
Don't worry.
别着急
We'll see him again.
我们还会见到他的
- When? - In time.
- 什么时候？ - 我们需要他的时候
One day he'll be here and the next he won't.
或许他第一天在， 可第二天就离开了
But you mustn't press him.
你没法强迫他
After all, he's not a tame lion.
毕竟，他不是只温顺的狮子
No.
不
But he is good.
但他很好
Here.
给你
You need it more than I do.
你比我更需要它
Are you all right, Philip?
菲利，你没事吧
I'm not as young as I once was.
我已经老了...
Come on, Ed.
快来啊，爱德蒙
- Catching my breath. - That's all we'll catch at this rate.
- 让我喘口气吧 - 照这样我们只能捉到这么多
- What did he say, Susan? - "Wait in the castle.
- 他说什么，苏珊？ - “在城堡里等着...
I'll get the stag myself."
...我自己就能捉到那头公鹿！”
What's this?
这是什么？
It seems familiar.
看上去很眼熟
As if from a dream.
似乎在梦里见过
Or a dream of a dream.
梦里的梦...
Spare Oom.
空房间！
- Lucy! - Not again.
- 露西！ - 别
- Lu? - Come on!
- 露西？ - 来！
These aren't branches.
他们不是树枝
- They're coats. - Susan, you're on my foot!
- 是大衣... - 苏珊，你踩我的脚了
Peter, move off!
彼得，闪开！
- Stop shoving. - Stop it!
- 别推啊！ - 够了！
I'm not on your toe!
我没踩你的脚！
There you are.
你们在这儿
What were you all doing in the wardrobe?
在我的衣厨里干什么？
You wouldn't believe us if we told you, sir.
您是不会相信我们的
Try me.
说说看
I don't think you'll get back in that way.
我不认为你们可以回去
You see... I've already tried.
我已经试过了
Will we ever go back?
我们还能回去吗？
Oh, I expect so.
噢，希望可以...
But it'll probably happen when you're not looking for it.
但只会发生在 你们没有刻意找它的时候
All the same...
尽管如此...
...best to keep your eyes open.
还是得睁大眼睛，注意观察...